A Guide to the Patricia Chalfant Women's Rights Collection, 1968-1978: SC 0240
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Patricia Chalfant Women's Rights Collection,
1968-1978
Special Collections, James Madison University
Chalfant, Patricia, 1941-2006
SC 0240
1.65 cubic feet; 3 boxes, 1 flat folder
The Patricia Chalfant Women's Rights Collection, 1968-1978, is comprised of publications, ephemera, and conference material documenting second-wave feminism and the women's liberation movement. Key subjects include the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), the National Organization for Women (NOW), and various organized marches including the July 9, 1978 March for the Equal Rights Amendment in Washington, D.C.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Received on December 12, 2015 from Reba Leiding, former librarian at JMU.
Provenance
This collection was orphaned in Reba Leiding's office in Carrier Library and she transferred the materials to Special Collections upon her retirement. The name Patricia Chalfant can be found on much of the materials, but no further information is known about the creator's connection to JMU or the collection's provenance. A collection inventory created by JMU student Emily Noonan was found in the box of Chalfant's materials. This document confirms that the material has been in the custody of JMU since at least 2006.
Bio/Historical Information
Patricia Jeanne Chalfant was born December 1, 1941 to Charles E. "Chap" Chalfant and Betty Hunter Chalfant of Christiana, Pennsylvania. She was a 1959 graduate of Octorara High School in Atglen, Pennsylvania and a 1962 graduate of Juniata College in Huntingdon, Pennsylvania. Chalfant continued her education by earning master's degrees from Drexel University and the University of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. She also attained her Juris Doctor from the Delaware Law School in 1985. Chalfant served as an attorney for the United States Navy and as Associate Council for the Defence National Stockpile. She was regarded by colleagues as being politically active and an advocate for women's rights. She was an active member of the National Organization for Women and served as the president of the Wilmington, Delaware chapter of NOW. Chalfant died December 7, 2006 and is interred at Glen Run Cemetery in Atglen, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Content
The Patricia Chalfant Women's Rights Collection, 1968-1978, is comprised of publications, ephemera, and conference material documenting second-wave feminism and the women's liberation movement. Key subjects include the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), the National Organization for Women (NOW), and various organized marches including the July 9, 1978 March for the Equal Rights Amendment in Washington, D.C.
Series 1: Publications, 1968-1978, comprises the bulk of the collection and includes newsletters, pamphlets, booklets and short published works on the topics of women's liberation, Title IX, the Equal Rights Amendment, and related feminist subjects.
Series 2: Conferences and Events, 1975-1978, documents national conferences, marches, and related women's rights events presumably attended by Patricia Chalfant. Materials from the 1975 (Philadelphia), 1977 (Detroit), and 1978 (Washington, D.C.) National Organization for Women national conferences are included. These materials include information on conference registration, program and lecture schedules, committees, election ballots, members, and getting around in the host city. Three folders of materials document the historic 1977 National Women's Conference in Houston, Texas. Newspaper clippings, information on conference programming and schedules, and member and delegate information provide additional context for this significant moment in the struggle for equal rights. Of particular interest are posters for a November 5, 1977 ERA rally and reception in Alexandria, Virginia. The event featured NOW President Eleanor Smeal and actresses Esther Rolle and Lily Tomlin. The oversize poster is signed by Lily Tomlin. Photographs are also included that document the 1978 ERA March on Washington.
Series 3: Ephemera, 1974-1978, includes blank postcards and note cards with feminist imagery, applied embroidery patterns for logos and feminist symbols, a broadside printed by Helaine Victoria Press, posters, ERA related stickers and sashes, and other miscellaneous items. Two oversize posters designed by feminist artist Judy Chicago are included.
Series 4: Oversize, 1975-1978, consists of one oversize flat file. The Oversize series consists of materials that have been physically removed from their intellectual arrangement due to their common size. The items in this series have been described in the previous series descriptions and as such, the Oversize series functions only as a container list.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 4 series:
Series 1: Publications, 1968-1978
Series 2: Conferences and Events, 1975-1978
Series 3: Ephemera, 1974-1978
Series 4: Oversize, 1975-1978
All series are arranged chronologically.
Bibliography
Obituary for Patricia Jeanne Chalfant, Intelligencer Journal (Lancaster, PA), December 11, 2006.
Index Terms
Subjects:
National Organization for Women -- History -- 20th century; Women's rights -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Feminism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Second-wave feminism -- United States; Women -- Political activity -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Equal rights amendments -- United States; Publications (documents); Pamphlets; Newsletters; Booklets; Posters
Genre and Form Terms:
Bylaws (administrative records); Color photographs; Printed Ephemera; Postcards; Embroidery (visual works); Stickers
- Series 1: Publications, 1968-1978
  - Toward a Female Liberation Movement by Beverly Jones and Judith Brown, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bread and Roses by Kathy McAfee and Myrna Wood, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sex Roles and Female Oppression: A Collection of Essays by Dana Densmore, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Social Construction of the Second Sex by Jo Freeman, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manglish by Varda One, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes from the Third Year: Women's Liberation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women's Liberation: An Anthropological View by Minda Borun, et al., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Women's Liberation Movement: Its Origins, Structures and Ideas by Jo Freeman, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Look Jane look. See sex stereotypes. by Women on Words and Images, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sisterhood is Powerful by Betsey Stone, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Twelve Steps to Non-Sexist Masculinity by Roslyn Rettew, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - The Monthly Extract: An Irregular Periodical, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Civil Rights Digest, Vol. 6 No. 3, Sexism and Racism: Feminist Perspectives, Spring 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Is Biology Woman's Destiny by Evelyn Reed, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Majority Wins: How to Build a Program for Legislative Change by Linda Joy, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Circle One: A Woman's Beginning Guide to Self Health and Sexuality, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Erotization of Male Dominance Female Submission by Ellen Morgan, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Feminist Revolution by Redstockings, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pennsylvania NOW, Vol. 3 No. 1, February 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - See How She Runs: Effective Political Techniques by Patricia Jo Smith, et al., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Tell-A-Woman, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Title IX, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Resource Booklet for Battered Spouses, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Women's Leadership Training Manual, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Aegis by Feminist Alliance Against Rape, September/October 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - March on Washington, July 9, 1978, For the Equal Rights Amendment: A Photographic Essay by Cully Miller and Chris Backus, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Lampoon Presents Claire Bretécher, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Resource Booklet for Families in Crisis, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Delaware Today Magazine, Update on Women: New Dawn or False Horizon?, November 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The Washington Equal Times, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Series 2: Conferences and Events, 1975-1978
  - Poster, International Women's Day, March 8, 1975 (Case Map, Folder 1)
  - National Organization for Women National Conference [SELECTED ITEMS REMOVED TO OVERSIZE], 1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Conference to Deal with Bylaws, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Organization for Women National Conference, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - ERA Stars in Virginia [SELECTED ITEMS REMOVED TO OVERSIZE], 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - National Women's Conference (Folder 1 of 3), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - National Women's Conference (Folder 2 of 3), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Women's Conference (Folder 3 of 3), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, ERA March on Washington, D.C., 1978 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National Organization for Women National Conference, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series 3: Ephemera, 1974-1978
  - Cards and Postcards, 1974-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Posters, Judy Chicago artwork, 1975, 1978 (Case Map, Folder 1)
  - Applied embroidery patterns, feminist imagery [SELECTED ITEMS REMOVED TO OVERSIZE], undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - ERA stickers, sashes, and ruler, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Helaine Victoria Press Broadside, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous [SELECTED ITEMS REMOVED TO OVERSIZE], undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series 4: Oversize, 1975-1978
  - Poster, International Women's Day, March 8, 1975 (Case Map, Folder 1)
  - Poster, National Organization for Women National Conference, 1975 (Case Map, Folder 1)
  - Posters, Judy Chicago artwork, 1975, 1978 (Case Map, Folder 1)
  - Poster, ERA Stars in Virginia, 1977 (Case Map, Folder 1)
  - Applied embroidery pattern, feminist imagery, undated (Case Map, Folder 1)
  - Bag, Helaine Victoria Press, undated (Case Map, Folder 1)